听译、时间轴：刘巍然（学酥）
大家好 欢迎来到分布式系统的第7课
Hello, everyone, and welcome to Lecture 7 of distributed systems.
今天我们将讨论复制的一致性
Today, we will be talking about consistency of replicas.
很不幸 “一致性”是一个很糟糕的词
Now, consistency is a bit of a terrible word, unfortunately,
因为这个词包含了太多的含义
because it means so many different things
这个词的含义与讨论的对象和讨论的上下文高度相关
depending on who you're asking and which context you're talking about.
你可能在一些上下文中见过一致性这个词
So, just some of the contexts where you might have seen consistency is
其中一个场景是事务一致性
in the context of transactions.
在ACID事务中 C表示的就是一致性
So, the ACID transaction, the C stands for consistency.
在这个上下文中 一致性是数据库状态要满足的一个性质
And in this context, the meaning of consistency is a property of a database state.
这里的一致性是指 数据库的状态是一致的
So, we're saying that the database is in a consistent state.
如果你在数据库上执行一个良定义的事务
And if you apply a good transaction to it,
则此事务会将数据库从一个一致性状态移动至另一个一致性状态
then it moves the database from one consistent state into another.
这里的一致性指的是
So, here consistent really means that
数据库状态要满足特定的不变性
the state of the database satisfies certain invariants
或满足应用设置的特定约束条件
or certain constraints that the application has set.
举个例子 如果你有一个大学数据库
As one example, if you have a university database,
你可能会设置一个一致性要求：
you might have a consistency requirement that
如果至少有一个学生注册了某个课程 则这个课程必须有一个讲师
whenever a course has at least one student enrolled in it, then it must also have a lecturer.
有学生注册的课程不可能没有讲师
So, it must not be without lecturer.
这只是举个例子 你可能会为数据库设置类似的一些约束性质
For example, you could have those kinds of consistency properties.
但实际上 ACID中的一致性
But this ACID consistency
与我们在分布式系统中讨论的一致性不一样
is not actually what we're usually talking about in distributed systems.
我们在前几节课中讲解过与之不同的一致性模型
We saw a different model of consistency a few lectures ago,
即读后写一致性
read-after-right consistency,
它的意思是 如果一个客户端写入数据 再读取刚刚写入的数据
which was that if a client makes a write and then reads back what it has just written,
则此客户端应该能读取到刚刚写入的数据
it should be able to see what it has just written.
这个一致性定义与ACID的一致性定义毫无关系
That has got nothing to do with the consistency in the sense of ACID.
一致性在这里表达了完全不同的含义
It's a very different meaning of the word.
在复制场景中 我们经常说
So, in the context of replication, what we often say is
我们希望一个副本与另一个副本保持一致
we want one replica to be consistent with another replica,
我们再一次面对“一致性”到底是什么意思的问题
which again raises the question of what exactly we mean.
意思是副本必须具有相同的状态？
So, does that mean the replicas are in the same state?
但副本到底要在什么时刻才必须具有相同的状态？
But when exactly do they have to be in the same states?
它们可以在不同的时间点具备相同的状态
They could be in the same state at different points in time, for example,
或者说同一时间点的状态可以不同吗？
or in different states at the same time?
我们会把一致性解读为
We could express consistency in terms of
读取操作的结果与我们期待的结果一样吗？
what the results of read operations should be what we expect?
我这里想强调的意思是 一致性有很多不同的含义
So, I'm just saying here there are lots of different forms of consistency.
不存在一个正确的一致性定义
And no one true definition of consistency.
实际上 有很多不同的一致性模型
There are in fact a whole bunch of different consistency models.
在本节课中 我们将学习一部分一致性模型
And in this lecture, we're going to look at some of those consistency models,
看看如何在特定的场景下定义和使用这些一致性模型
and see the context in which they are useful and how they are defined.
我想先从分布式事务开始讲起
So, what I want to start with is distributed transactions.
大家在前半部分的并发系统课程中已经学习了事务的概念
So, you've covered transactions in the first half of this course on concurrent systems.
回忆一下ACID性质 A代表原子性
And if you recall the ACID properties, the A stands for atomicity,
意思是 如果一个事务对数据库进行了一系列更新
which means that if a transaction makes a bunch of updates to the database,
则如果数据库崩溃或出现了什么错误
then even if the database crashes or something goes wrong,
或者所有更新都被应用在数据库上并完成持久性存储
either all of those updates are applied to the database and they are made durable,
此时称事务被提交
in which case the transaction is set to commit,
或者所有更新都没有生效
or none of the updates take effect,
此时称事务被中止
in which case the transaction is said to be aborted.
事务有二选一的可能性 或者被提交、或者被中止
So, we have this kind of binary choice of a transaction, either it commits, or it aborts,
但我们不会以中间状态结束事务
but we don't end up with this kind of half state,
即事务中的有些更新已经生效
where some of the transaction updates have happened,
而其余更新还没有生效
and others have not have happened.
这非常重要
And this is very important,
如果你想让数据库系统满足ACID下的一致性
because if you want to ensure something like consistency in the sense of ACID,
则原子性是一致性的基础
you do have to have atomicity as the foundation of that,
否则 你可能就需要通过某种方式
because otherwise, you could end up with
协调两个数据库更改操作
two changes that need to be coordinated in some way,
如果只有一个更改操作生效 你就会得到不一致的数据库状态
and if only one of the two happens, then you end up in an inconsistent state.
这就是我们为什么需要原子性的原因
So, that's why we need atomicity.
在分布式系统中 执行一个事务
Now, in a distributed system, we might have a transaction
可能会涉及到分布式数据库的多个节点
that involves more than one node in a distributed database, for example.
在此类系统中 我们需要保证
And in this type of system, we have to ensure atomicity
参与此次事务的所有节点都满足原子性
across all of the nodes that are participating in the transaction,
也就是说 涉及此事务所有节点的数据读取或写入操作都需要满足原子性
so, all of the nodes on which data is being read or written in the course of a transaction.
因此 我们必须保证事务在所有节点或者都被提交
And so, we must ensure that the transaction either commits on all of the nodes,
或者都被中止
or it aborts on all of the nodes.
这样才能让事务作为一个整体
So, that would then give us atomicity for the transaction as a whole
在所有节点上满足原子性
across all of the nodes.
进一步 如果涉及此事务的其中一个节点崩溃
Moreover, if one of the nodes involved in the transaction crashes,
我们同样必须要求所有其他节点也要中止此事务
then we also have to make sure that we abort the transaction on all other nodes,
因为崩溃节点无法完成此事务
because the crash node cannot complete the transaction,
此节点无法提交此事务
it cannot commit the transaction.
在分布式系统中 这被称为原子提交问题
And this is known as the atomic commitment problem in distributed systems.
你可能会觉得 这看起来和共识有点像
So, you might think this looks kind of a bit similar to consensus,
因为我们这里也希望所有节点
because what we want here is all of the nodes to agree on
对提交或中止事务达成一致
whether to commit or abort the transaction,
细细品味 这和共识确实很像
which kind of smells like consensus.
表面上的确很像
Now, yes, superficially.
但如果我们深入到细节就会发现
But if we look at it in more detail,
实际上 原子提交和共识完全不同
actually, atomic commitment is quite different from consensus.
让我来解释一下原因
And so, let me just explain why.
我前面解释过共识的定义
With consensus, the way I explained it previously was that
你有多个节点 一个或多个节点提出了某个值
you have multiple nodes, one or more node may propose some value,
共识协议将决定选择哪个值
and one of those values gets decided by the consensus algorithm,
而原子提交的约束条件更强
whereas in atomic commits, we're a bit more constrained.
我们必须让所有的节点进行投票
We have to have all of the nodes voting on
一起来判断是否提交一个事务
whether they are able to commit a transaction or not.
我们必须要考虑所有节点的投票结果
And we have to take all of those votes into account.
在共识中
So, while in consensus,
我们可以简单地选择节点提出的其中一个值
it's OK to simply pick any one of the values that has been proposed.
原子提交清楚地定义了必须发生的事情
In atomic commit, it's very clearly defined what must happen.
如果所有的节点都投票给提交 则必须提交事务
If all of the nodes vote to commit, then the transaction must commit.
如果任意一个节点投票给中止 则所有节点必须中止事务
If any one of the nodes votes to abort, then all of them must abort.
因此 在算法进行决策时
So, atomic commit is much more constrained
原子提交的约束条件更强
in the decision that the algorithm has to make.
最后 在共识中
And finally, with consensus,
我们可以提出Raft这样的算法
we've seen that we can have algorithms like Raft,
只要quorum节点可以接收和响应请求
which can continue working
算法就可以继续工作
as long as a quorum of nodes is reachable and responding to requests,
但在原子提交中
whereas with atomic commit,
因为我们要求所有节点都必须要投票
because we have this requirement that all of the nodes must vote,
我们必须让所有节点达成共识
and we must get consensus across all of them,
这意味着
this means now that
即使只存在一个崩溃节点 整个事务都需要被中止
even just one single node crash will cause the entire transaction to abort.
原子提交无法容忍任何故障节点
So, atomic commit is not able to tolerate any faulty nodes,
而像Raft这样的容错共识算法
whereas a fault-tolerant consensus algorithm like Raft
可以容忍系统中出现少半故障节点
is able to tolerate a minority of faulty nodes in the system.
这就是原子提交的概念
So, this is atomic commitment.
我们通常实现原子提交的方法是
And the way we typically implement atomic commit is
使用一个叫两阶段提交的算法
using an algorithm called two-phase commit.
两阶段提交听起来有点像
Now two-phase commit sounds a bit like two-phase locking,
大家在前面学习过的两阶段锁定
which you've seen previously.
不要把两个名词弄混 这两个名词听起来很相似 但它们完全不同
Don't confuse the two. They sound very similar, but they're very different things.
两阶段锁定是实现串行化隔离的技术
So, two-phase locking is around serializable isolation
两阶段提交是实现原子提交的技术
whereas two-phase commit is around getting atomicity,
完全不同的领域
very different area.
我们开始执行两阶段提交的方式是
So, the way we start two-phase commit is that
客户端希望在多个数据库节点上启动一个事务
the client wants to begin a transaction on multiple database nodes.
客户端像往常一样启动一个事务
And it just starts a transaction as usual,
向这些节点发送事务标识符T_1 并像往常一样执行此事务
sends some transaction identifier T_1 to those nodes, and then, does its usual thing,
事务会从数据库中读取或写入任意对象
so, the transaction may read and write arbitrary objects in the database,
完成它需要执行的任意业务逻辑
and do whatever it needs to do any kind of logic.
只有当我们准备好提交事务时 才会启动两阶段提交
Two-phase commit only starts when we're ready to commit the transaction.
我们不按照通常的方式提交事务
So, rather than the usual form of transaction commits
客户端不能直接发送给数据库一条消息 说：“请现在提交吧”
where the client just sends directly to the database, “Hey, commit now please”.
在两阶段提交中
With two-phase commit, instead,
提交请求会被发送给系统中的一个新节点
the request to commit goes to a new node in the system
此节点被称为事务协调者
called the transaction coordinator.
此提交请求会被发送给事务协调者
So, this commit request goes to the coordinator.
协调者接下来
And the coordinator then sends a prepare message
向所有参与此事务的数据库节点发送一条准备消息
to all of the database nodes that are participating in the transaction.
发送准备消息的目的是
And the purpose of the prepare message is
让节点几乎执行完事务 只是还没有最终提交事务
it's kind of like commit, except it doesn't actually finish the transaction yet.
也就是说 当数据库节点收到准备消息时
So, what prepare does is when a database node receives the prepare message,
数据库节点必须
the database node has to
向磁盘写入此事务包含的所有更新操作
write all of the changes, all of the updates from that transaction to disk,
数据库节点必须检查约束条件 满足数据库的一致性要求
and it has to check any constraints to make sure that we have consistency of the database,
因为当回复这条准备消息时
because in response to that prepare message,
数据库节点需要回复“是”或者“否”
the database node now has to reply with either yes or no,
表示数据库节点是否愿意提交此事务
whether it's willing to commit that transaction or not.
我前面说过 只要有一个节点回复“否” 都会导致事务中止
And so, as we said, any one no response to this will cause the transaction to abort.
但如果所有节点都回复“是” 就会提交此事务
But if all of them vote yes, then the transaction will commit.
这意味着一旦数据库节点回复称：
So, this means that once the database node replies, saying,
“我很高兴能够提交此事务”
“OK, I'm happy to commit this transaction”,
数据库节点就会保证未来它已经能够提交此事务
it is promising that it will definitely be able to commit that transaction in the future,
因为在这个时刻 数据库节点已经履行完它的职责了
because at this point, the database node has abdicated its responsibility.
现在轮到事务协调者决定
Now, it's up to the transaction coordinator to make the decision
是否提交此事务了
whether or not to commit the transaction.
数据库节点必须保证
So, the database node just has to promise that
如果协调者随后要求数据库节点提交事务
if it is asked later by the coordinator to commit the transaction,
那么数据库节点就一定能提交此事务
it will definitely be able to commit it.
我们不允许数据库节点事后退出或离开 告诉我们：
So, it's not allowed to back out and flake out afterwards, and say,
“不好意思 我不想提交了”
“Oh, sorry, I don't want to commit this after all”.
这时候再反悔就太晚了
because by that point, it's too late.
准备消息告诉事务处理节点
So, the prepare message is telling the trade-based nodes that
它们必须准备好提交事务
it must get everything ready to be able to commit,
只是还没有最终提交事务
but without actually ending the transaction yet.
随后 如果在两阶段提交的步骤2中
And then, if the coordinator says in phase 2 of two-phase commit,
协调者说：“我们现在提交吧”
if the coordinator says, “OK, now we're going to commit”,
则独立数据库节点继续处理
then the individual database nodes go.
它们完成提交、终止事务、释放所有的锁
They do the actual commit. They end the transaction. They release all of the locks.
一切处理完毕
And everything is done.
这就是两阶段提交的模型
So, this is the model of two-phase commit.
此协议最关键的时刻在这里
And the key moment in this protocol is here.
当参与节点回复给协调者
So, after the participating nodes have replied to the coordinator,
告诉协调者是否愿意提交此事务时
saying whether or not they're willing to commit this transaction,
在这一时刻 协调者将决定提交事务还是中止事务
at this point, the coordinator makes the decision whether to commit or abort.
这的确是此协议最关键的时刻
And this is really a key moment in the protocol.
现在 我们可以考虑一下 如果一些节点崩溃 会发生什么
Now, we can think about what happens if some of these nodes crash.
如果数据库节点崩溃 则我们已经讨论过
So, if the database node crashes, then we've discussed that
这意味着事务协调者将会发现响应超时
that means the transaction coordinator will timeout,
它会说：“每个人都中止事务吧”
and it will say, “OK, we're going to abort the transaction for everyone”.
这没什么问题
So, that's fine.
问题是 如果协调者崩溃 会发生什么
The question is what happens if the coordinator crashes.
如果协调者崩溃
So, if the coordinator crashes, well,
它可能已经作出了是否中止或提交事务的决定
first of all, it has to make this decision on whether to abort or commit the transaction.
它可以把决定写入磁盘
So, it can write that decision to disk.
当协调者随后从崩溃中恢复 重新回到岗位后
And so, then, when the coordinator recovers from its crash and starts back up again,
它可以从磁盘中读取决定 并把已经作出的决定
it can read this decision from disk, and send the decision that it made
发送给参与此次事务的所有副本
to the replicas that were participating in the transaction.
如果磁盘中没有决策记录 则协调者可以直接中止事务
Or, if there was no decision record on disk, then the coordinator can just abort.
但是 协调者必须做到的是 如果协调者崩溃
But it has to be even if the coordinator crashes,
且如果协调者在崩溃前已经决定提交事务
if it made the decision before the crash to commit,
那么协调者必须在重启后继续诚实地发送提交事务的决定
then it must honor that decision after it restarts,
因为协调者可能已经把提交消息
because it might have already
发送给了部分节点 但还没有发送给所有的节点
sent the commit message to some of the nodes, but not all of them.
因此 一些节点可能已经完成提交 释放了所有的锁
And so, some of the nodes may have already committed and released all of their locks.
此时 我们需要保证其它节点也要提交事务
So now, we have to ensure that everybody else commits as well.
类似地 如果一个节点中止 则其它所有节点也必须中止
And likewise, if one aborts, then all of the others have to abort as well.
但这留给了我们一个问题
But this leaves us in a problem,
协调方现在成为了协议的卡点
because the coordinator is now this linchpin in this protocol,
如果协调者崩溃的时间点刚好为
because if the coordinator crashes
协调者已经发送出准备请求
just at the moment after the prepare requests have been sent out,
但还没有发送出
but before the coordinator sent out its decision on
是否提交或中止事务的决定时
whether to commit or abort the transaction,
此时 所有其他节点都不知道协调方作出了什么决定
then all of the other nodes don't know what the coordinator has decided it.
它们会被卡住 它们无法终止事务
They are simply stuck. They cannot end their transaction yet.
它们不能中止事务
They can't abort their transaction,
因为我前面说过 它们必须保证它们有能力提交事务
because as I said earlier, they have promised that they will be able to commit it.
如果它们中止了事务 它们就无法保证有能力提交事务了
So, if they abort it, then they wouldn't be able to commit it anymore.
因此 它们不能提交或中止它们的事务
So, they can't commit or abort their transaction.
它们都会被卡在这种不确定事务状态的阶段中
They're all stuck in this state of being uncertain of what the state of the transaction is.
因此 独立节点无法自主决定提交还是中止事务
And so, the individual nodes can't just decide for themselves to abort or commit,
因为这会引入违反原子性的风险
because that would risk violating atomicity.
因此 整个算法都被阻塞住了
So, the entire algorithm is blocked
直到协调方重启 并通过磁盘上的数据恢复它的状态
until the coordinator restarts and recovers its state from disk.
这可不太妙
So, this is not great,
因为如果协调者崩溃 它可能需要花费一定的时间才能再次回归
because if a coordinator crashes, it might take a while to come back up again.
如果运行协调者的机器遇到了硬件故障
If the machine where the coordinator was running on experience the hardware failure,
那就更糟糕了 因为得有个人
it's even worse, because somebody has to go
把机器中的磁盘取出来 放到一台新机器上
and take the hard disk out of that machine and put it into a new machine, and so on.
此时 整个系统都会瘫痪
So, the whole system could be down and locked up
在相当长的一段时间内处于锁定状态
for quite a significant amount of time.
幸运的是 有种方法可以解决这个问题
Fortunately, there is a way around this.
有一种两阶段提交的变种算法 此算法具有容错性
And there is an algorithm, a variant of two-phase commit that is fault-tolerant.
此算法依赖于我们上一节课讨论的技术
And it relies on what we talked about in the last lecture,
依赖全序关系广播 又名共识算法
on total order broadcast a.k.a., consensus algorithm.
算法的工作原理如下 这个算法只有两页幻灯片长
And it works like this. This algorithm is just two slides long.
算法的基本思想是 我们使用全序关系广播算法
And the idea here is that we use a total order broadcast algorithm
来散布每个节点有关提交或中止的投票结果
to disseminate each node's vote on whether to abort or to commit.
每一个节点都会存储一些状态
And so, for each node, we're going to have some state here.
对于每一个事务 我们初始化一个集合（commitVotes）
So, for each transaction, we're going to have a set here
此集合包含为此事务投提交票的所有副本id
containing the replica ids that have voted in favor of committing a certain transaction.
我们还初始化一个集合（replicas） 包含参与此事务的所有节点
We have the set of all of the replicas that are participating in a certain transaction.
对于每一个事务 我们还设置一个标识（decided）
And for each transaction, we have a flag
此标识告诉我们是否已经作出了决定
telling us whether we have decided yet or not.
现在 当我们想提交一个事务
And so, now, when we want to commit a transaction,
我们按照协调者通常的做法进行操作
we do the same as we do what the coordinator would usually do, which is
我们向参与此事务的所有节点发送一条准备消息
it just sends a prepare message to all of the nodes participating in the transaction.
这就是和之前一样的常规准备消息
OK, that's just a regular prepare message as before.
当一个节点或一个副本收到了这条准备消息
When a node or a replica receives this prepare message,
它就知道了参与此事务的所有副本所构成的集合 称这个集合为R
it now knows the set of replicas that are participating in this transaction called R.
此副本记录下此集合 这就是参与事务T的副本集合
So, it remembers that. This is the set of replicas participating in transaction T.
现在 和之前一样
And now, as before,
副本需要检查自己是否有能力提交此事务
the replica needs to check whether it is able to commit the transaction.
它随后要用“是”或“否”来回复准备请求
And it will reply to the prepare request, saying either yes or no.
如果副本回复“是” 它必须保证
And if it says yes, it promises that
自己在未来一定能够提交此事务
we'll definitely be able to commit this transaction in the future.
这里的ok就是一个布尔值 表示“是”或“否”
So, this ok will simply be a Boolean here, saying true or false,
即此副本是否有能力提交此事务
whether it is able to commit the transaction or not.
现在 我们不把投票发送回协调者
And now, rather than sending this vote back to the coordinator,
我们使用全序关系广播
we use total order broadcast to
将此投票发送给所有参与此事务的副本
send this vote to all of the replicas that are participating in this transaction.
现在 所有副本互相都将知道谁有能力提交哪个事务
So now, all of the replicas find out about each other of who is able to commit what.
这几乎要达到我们的目的了
And this gets us most of the way there.
现在的问题是 如果其中一个副本崩溃了 该怎么办
The question is just what if one of these replicas has crashed.
如果一个节点已经崩溃 则这个节点就无法广播投票
And so, if that replica has crashed, then it is not able to broadcast its vote.
因此 所有节点都将卡在这里 一直等待下去 但此投票永远不会出现
So, all of the others would be stuck waiting forever until this vote never turns up.
因此 我们额外需要的是一个失效检查器
So, what we have in addition is a failure detector.
失效检查器可以运行在任意节点上
And this failure detector, this can be running on any node,
例如 可以运行在其他数据库副本上 甚至可以运行在客户端上
for example, on some of the other database replicas, or even on the client.
此失效检查器只是检查并怀疑某个副本是否已经出现了故障
And it just checks whether it suspects any of the replicas to have failed.
如果某个节点向某个副本发送了准备请求
So, if it has sent the prepare request to some replica,
但此副本在一定时间内没有广播它的投票 此节点的投票超时了
and the replica has not broadcast its vote yet after some amount of time, some time out,
则运行失效检查器的节点将代表此副本广播一个投票
then this other node is just going to broadcast a vote on behalf of the replica
内容是它怀疑此副本出现了故障 它代替此副本投“否”
that it has suspected to have failed, and it just votes false.
也就是说 此节点将代表此副本投中止票
So, it votes to abort on behalf of this replica.
你可以看到 现在可能发生的一件事情是
Now, what could happen, as you can see here, is that actually, it could be that
被怀疑已经崩溃的节点可能并没有真正崩溃
the replica here that is suspected to have crashed hasn't actually crashed.
它可能还好好的 只是消息处理的有点慢
It might be fine. It might just be a bit slow.
因此 我们可能在几乎相同的时刻
And so, it could be that just around about the same time,
得到两个针对同一副本的不同投票结果
we get two conflicting votes for the same replica,
一个是副本本身发送的真实投票
that is, one genuine vote from the replica that the replica itself is sending,
一个是来自其他一个甚至多个副本的投票
and one vote or maybe even several votes from other replicas
它们认为这个副本已经出现了故障
who think this particular node has failed.
我们现在要依赖全序关系广播的性质
And so, now, we are relying on the property of total order broadcast,
即系统中的所有参与方、系统中的所有节点
which is all of the participants, all of the nodes in the system
都将按照相同的顺序传递相同的消息
will deliver the same messages in the same order.
正式这个性质
And because of that,
使得针对相同副本的不同投票结果不会出现竞争问题
this race between the different votes for the same replica is no longer a problem,
因为我们可以保证
because we can ensure that
所有节点看到的第一个针对给定副本的投票结果都是一样的
the first vote that we see from a given replica will be the same for all of the nodes.
因此 这意味着
And so, this means, here,
我们无论通过全序关系广播传递了哪一个投票结果
whenever we deliver one of these votes here by total order broadcast,
我们只需要考虑给定副本的第一个投票结果 忽略未来所有的投票结果
we can just consider the first vote from any given replica and ignore any future votes.
这将保证所有节点都会作出相同的决定
And this will ensure that all of the nodes then come to the same decision
判断是中止还是提交事务
as to whether to abort or commit the transaction.
首先
So, first of all, here,
如果投票的副本不在已经投提交票的副本集合中
if the replica that is voting is not already one of the votes that has committed,
且如果副本是参与事务T的副本
and if the replica is one of the replicas in the transaction T,
且我们还没有为事务T作出决定
and we have not already made a decision for transaction T,
则这里的ok决定了此节点的投票结果为“是”还是“否”
then, well, ok depends whether we voted in favor or not.
如果投票结果为“是” 意思是投票给提交事务
So, if we voted true, which means vote in favor of committing,
我们将此副本的id（replicaId）添加至
then we add the replica id to the set of replicas
投票给支持提交事务的副本集合中
that have voted in favor of committing this particular transaction.
如果投提交票的副本所构成的集合
And if this set of replicas that have voted in favor
等于所有参与此事务的全部副本所构成的集合
equals the set of all replicas participating in the transaction,
这意味着我们现在得到了统一的投票结果
that means now we have the unanimity that we require.
我们可以决定提交此事务 并在此节点完成提交操作
We can decide to commit the transaction and do the actual commit at this node.
另一方面 如果其中一个投票为“否” 即表示反对提交
On the other hand, if the vote was false, it was in against committing,
这意味着我们可以立刻中止
that means we can immediately abort,
因为一个反对票已经足以让我们抛弃整个事务了
because one single vote against is already enough to discard the whole transaction.
我们可以将decided标识设置为“真”
We can set our flag to be decided to be true,
我们在这个节点中止事务
and then we're going to abort the transaction at this node.
如果你仔细考虑一下 我们这里的逻辑保证
And if you think about this, the logic that we have here ensures that
我们只需要考虑任意给定副本的第一个投票结果
we only count the first vote from any given replica,
因为所有节点都会约定好按照相同的顺序传递投票结果
and because all of the nodes will agree when they're delivering these votes.
它们会约定好给定副本的第一张投票结果是什么
They will agree on which the first vote was from a given replica.
这将保证所有参与方都可以看到相同的投票结果
This will ensure that all of the participants see the same
并针对提交还是中止此事务作出相同的决定
and come to the same decision as to whether to commit or abort this transaction.
这个协议很不错吧？
Isn't that nice?
我们有了全序关系广播算法
We have this total order broadcast algorithm,
我们以一种相当简单的方式用它来解决这个完全不同的问题
and we can use it to solve this quite different problem in a reasonably simple way.